Norman Corwin Papers
Norman Corwin Papers
- Productions of Corwin
  - Radio programs, individual
    - You Can Dream, Inc., Columbia Presents Corwin, Season 1 #6
      - Recording
        - You Can Dream, Inc. [disc 2 of 2], 04/11/1944; corwin_0129; Lacquer discs/acetates
      - Script (121), 1944; final broadcast script (Box 24)
  - Songs
    - Songs: "Go Down Death" and "The Fust Banjo", 01/15/1939; corwin_0345; Lacquer discs/acetates
      In his first year at CBS, Corwin tried his hand at musical composition, and wrote settings for two pieces done on the WORDS WITHOUT MUSIC broadcast of Jan. 15, 1939. These were arranged and sung by the Golden Gate Quartet. This disc contains a performance of both songs.
  - Speeches
    - Brandeis Institute stag dinner, 1961 (Box 24)
      Transferred from Franz Waxman Papers, 1968
    - for Alan Cranston (247), 1968; campaign speech for U.S. Senate; typescript draft with corrections (Box 24)
    - Talk by Norman Corwin for Canadian Red Cross, 03/14/1945; corwin_0358; recorded in Toronto, Ontario; Lacquer discs/acetates
    - Control your thoughts, mister? (209), 1947; keynote address at conference on thought control; typescript draft with corrections, printed conference announcement (Box 24)
    - for Edward G. Robinson (154), 1965; luncheon at Robinson's home on behalf of United Jewish Welfare Fund; includes two letters and printed program (Box 24)
    - Explanation marks on "The Hyphen" (198), 1966 (Box 24)
      Remarks delivered by Corwin at a luncheon given in his honor by the University of Utah, as published in The Utah Alumnus. Also included is a printed program from a performance of the play directe by Corwin and starring William Shatner (the program notes, "Mr. Shatner will star in the new television series Star Trek, which will be released on NBC in the fall").
    - Franz Waxman Memorial Concert (227), 1968; typescript draft with corrections; thank-you letter; printed program (Box 24)
    - for Lewis Milestone (179), 1955; for San Francisco Film Festival; carbon copy of typescript (Box 24)
    - Marie Hanson Wesley eulogy (314), 1969; typescript with corrections (Box 24)
      See also Correspondence: Wesley, Marie Hanson.
    - One world revisited (105), 1946; notes; typescript; reprint of published text (Box 24)
    - Public image of music (182), 1965; for Chamber Symphony Society of California; typescript with corrections (photocopy); also includes a few letters and two printed programs (Box 24)
    - Set your clock at U-235 (324), 1945; for New York Herald Tribune Forum, read by Paul Robeson; typescript draft with corrections (Box 24)
      See also Radio programs: Set your clock at U-235 and Productions of others: Ryan, Robert.
    - Tribute to Aaron Rosenberg (186), read by Bill Gordon; photocopy of draft (Box 17)
  - Stage plays
    - The Chinese Wall
      - Correspondence (68, 245), 1962; undated; includes contract (Box 24)
      - Publicity (68, 245), 1962; program (2 copies), clippings, reviews (Box 24)
      - Script (68), 1962; includes budget, music cue sheets, interview list, cast list (with extras), original typescript (Box 24)
    - Citizen of the World
      - Script (60), 1962; adaptation by Robert Preswell; photocopy of typescript; includes brief note from Preswell (Box 24)
    - Eleanor Roosevelt Memorial Program
      - Correspondence (35), includes printed invitation set from Adlai Stevenson and program (Box 24)
      - Script elements (35), 1963; various elements from show, including lighting cue sheet, biographical notes about participants, typed and handwritten notes, etc. (Box 25)
    - The Lincoln-Douglas Debates
      See also The Rivalry and Tonight! Lincoln vs Douglas.
      - Correspondence (13), 1954-1956; George Jessel, Dan Goldberg, Irving Harris, also Corwin's agent Leah Salisbury; regarding options on the play (Box 25)
      - Extracts from original debates (12), undated; typed extracts from the 21 hours of the original debates, used as raw material for dramatization (Box 25)
    - Memorandum to Jeremiah, starred Carl Sandburg as Jeremiah, the only time Sandburg ever appeared as an actor
      - Correspondence (73), 1961; includes abridged version of play created by Hadassah, the women's Zionist organization; text of Ambassador Harman's remarks to Sandburg; review from Heritage Southwest Jewish Press (Box 25)
      - Script (73), 1961; includes large-print sheets for Sandburg's use (Box 25)
    - Odyssey of Runyon Jones
      See also Radio programs: The Odyssey of Runyon Jones.
      - Manuscript (305), 1941 (Box 25)
      - Script (76), 1941; typescript with corrections (Box 25)
    - Overkill and Megalove
      - Program and syllabus (329), 1956; published as Festival Theatre Student Study Series Syllabus IV, signed by Corwin; booklet includes remarks by Corwin, analysis and discussion of plays, etc. (Box 25)
      - Script (150), 1956; original typescript with corrections (Box 25)
    - The Rivalry
      See also The Lincoln-Douglas Debates and Tonight! Lincoln vs Douglas.
      - Correspondence, 1954-1964; undated; Leah Salisbury, Corwin's agent; Cheryl Crawford and Joel Schencker, directors of Broadway production; others; 2 folders (Box 25)
      - Correspondence, Paul Gregory, 1956-1959; relating to national tour; Leah Salisbury, Corwin's agent; others (Box 25)
      - Notes, research material, analysis of debate text, notes about what was actually worn during the debates, drafts of script fragments, more (Box 26)
      - Publicity, Broadway production (28), 1958-1959; reviews, advertisements, program; 2 folders (Box 26)
      - Publicity, national tour (19), 1957-1958; reviews, advertisements, programs from performances around the country; 2 folders (Box 26)
      - Script (31), undated; small typed label says "Broadway version" (Box 26)
      - Script (31), Aug 1958; "Master" handwritten on front (Box 26)
      - Script (31), Sep 1958; incomplete; front page says "master pages removed[...]when sent to Dick Boone" (Box 26)
      - Script (27), 1960; published version, Dramatists Play Service (Box 26)
      - Script (31), 1959; "stage manager's copy" written and crossed out; numerous edits, corrections, annotations (Box 26)
      - Script (31), includes notes to Martin Gabel, who played Douglas, on yellow insert sheets (Box 26)
      - Statements (20, 26), 1957-1959; box office and royalty (Box 27)
    - Tonight! Lincoln versus Douglas
      See also The Lincoln-Douglas Debates and The Rivalry.
      - Publicity (14), 1956-1957; reviews in Los Angeles area; press on play (Box 27)
      - Scripts (31), 1956; three different versions, with notes, corrections, additions, etc.; 2 folders (Box 27)
    - Tribute to Carl Sandburg
      - Correspondence (8), 1958 (Box 27)
      - Publicity (8), 1958 (Box 27)
      - Script (8), 1958; master script with corrections; also includes cast list, rehearsal schedule (Box 27)
    - White Alice, Corwin's production of play by James Clavell
      - Correspondence (380), 1960; includes copy of contract (Box 27)
      - Scripts (379), circa 1960; two versions, both with annotations, edits, corrections, notes; 2 folders (Box 27)
      - Set designs (379), circa 1960; drawings and sketches (Box 27)
      - Miscellaneous (379), circa 1960; interview list; research material and notes (Box 27)
    - The World of Carl Sandburg
      - Correspondence (6), 1958-1961; includes typed list of Sandburg works from which the performance was drawn; 2 folders (Box 28)
      - Publicity (7), 1959-1960; clippings, reviews, theater programs (Box 28)
      - Script, published (9), 1961; Samuel French edition (Box 28)
  - Television programs
    - America at Work, Corwin's first network broadcast
      - Script on railroading, 1938 (Box 28)
    - Boomerang, written under Corwin's pseudonym Donald Cormorant
      - Script, 1949 (Box 28)
    - The FDR Series
      - Correspondence (32), 1960-1962; includes transcripts of speeches, photograph list, episode breakdown, more (Box 28)
      - Research material and notes (33), 1956-1962 (Box 28)
      - The Roosevelt Years (33), undated; transcript of lengthy interview with Mrs Roosevelt about FDR, original source unknown; Corwin's notes on front (Box 28)
      - Typescripts (34), undated; some incomplete, some annotated (Box 28)
    - The Human Angle
      - Script (83), 1950; carbon copy with corrections, edits, etc. (Box 28)
        See also Radio programs, individual: The Human Angle.
    - On a Note of Triumph, television version of radio program orginally broadcase on VE Day, 1945
      - Photographs (229), undated; images used in production, some very graphic; a few original photos but most are clipped from print sources and folded with crop-mark overlays (Box 29)
      - Publicity (229), 1966 (Box 29)
    - Pursuit of Happiness
      - Typescript fragment (371), carbon copy with corrections, edits, etc.; written by William Saroyan with notes by Corwin (Box 29)
    - The Seven Seas (Sette Mari)
      - Scripts (488), circa 1968; seven scripts; includes notes on introductory scenes, etc.; 2 folders (Box 29)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Case for clemency, 1960; statement on Caryl Chessman case published in the Los Angeles Times; Corwin is one of 127 signers/sponsors (Box 29)
    - Confidential report on the BBC, 1942; written at request of William S. Paley (Box 29)
    - Flight to the Moon (294), 1969; narration for documentary about Apollo 11 moon landing; manuscript drafts, typescript drafts, final (Box 29)
    - The Gagster and the Poet (226, 332), 1947; 2 folders (Box 29)
      This was a meeting at Corwin's home with Corwin, Carl Sandburg and television producer Hal Kanter. The meeting was tape recorded and later published as an article. Material includes a transcript of the recording with notes, galleys of the article and clippings of the article as published in WEST Magazine, part of the Los Angeles Times.
    - The Golden Web (331), 1969; Corwin's review of book by Erik Barnouw (Box 29)
    - The Grand Alliance, 24 Oct 1953; recording; corwin_0286; Lacquer discs/acetates
      Written for broadcast on United Nations Day, October 24, 1953. Produced by Gerald Kean, written and directed by Corwin, for United Nations Radio. THE GRAND ALLIANCE was also the title of a documentary film Corwin wrote for the UN.
    - Vietnam War statement (376), 1967; manuscript, typescript (Box 29)
    - Watts Towers (118), 1959; efforts to save Watts Towers in Los Angeles; clippings of pieces by Corwin and Sandburg; photographs (Box 29)
    - United Nations First Anniversary Dinner
      Donor information: "On April 25, 1946, the first anniversary of the founding of the United Nations was celebrated at a dinner in the grand ballroom of the Hotel Astor in New York City. The host organization was The Independent Citizens Committee of the Arts, Sciences and Professions, of which Harold Ickes was chairman, and Corwin one of the national vice-presidents. Corwin served as chairman of the dinner, and introduced Ickes, and four members of the U. N.'s Security Council - Sir Alexander Cadogan, Henri Bonnet of France, Quo Ti Chi of Nationalist China, and Andrei Gromyko of the U.S.S.R. Also Trygve Lie, Secretary General of the UN, as well as Charles Collingwood, Theodore White, William L. Shirer, Bill Downs, and Joseph C. Harsh. Corwin conceived the components and structure of the program, at the invitation of the Arts and Sciences Committee." Believed only copy extant. Broadcast over WABC, New York City.
      - United Nations First Anniversary Dinner Part 1 of 3, 25 Apr 1946; corwin_0325; Lacquer discs/acetates
      - United Nations First Anniversary Dinner Part 2 of 3, 25 Apr 1946; corwin_0326; Lacquer discs/acetates
      - United Nations First Anniversary Dinner Part 3 of 3, 25 Apr 1946; corwin_0327; Lacquer discs/acetates
- Productions of others
  - Allen, Fred / radio program, untitled, Corwin as guest
    On May 14, 1944, Fred Allen presented Corwin as a guest on his regular weekly program over CBS. The two had long been friends, although this was the only time they appeared together on a broadcast. Allen's writers prepared the script.
    - Corwin as Guest on Fred Allen Program [disc 1 of 2], corwin_0220; Lacquer discs/acetates
    - Corwin as Guest on Fred Allen Program [disc 2 of 2], corwin_0221; Lacquer discs/acetates
  - BBC / Sounds of War
    Actual recordings of combat sounds, made by the BBC and presented to Corwin for use in his London-based series, AN AMERICAN IN ENGLAND, in 1942. Each disc bears the stamp "Passed For Security," a date, and a signature.
    - The Sounds of War [disc 1 of 5], corwin_0353; Shellac disc
      Included on this disc are the sounds of: A night raid on London, September, 1940; a stick of 5 bombs exploding; wardens on patrol; sound of an enemy bomber overhead; anti-aircraft fire, bombs fall; the attack dies away; time bombs falling; anti-aircraft fire and warden's patrol (dated 9/27/40)
    - The Sounds of War [disc 2 of 5], corwin_0354; Shellac disc
      Included on this disc are the sounds of: Bursts of Tommy guns; machine gun and rifle fire; 75mm field guns (French 75s); trench mortar firing; heavy explosion; falling debris; machine gun and rifle fire; hand grenades; burst from Bren gun, with ricochet; 6 shots from .303 revolver; 6 shots from .45
    - The Sounds of War [disc 3 of 5], corwin_0355; Shellac disc
      Included on this disc are the sounds of: Spitfire starting up and taxiing away; 5 Spitfires taking off; 4 Spitfires flying low; 2 Spitfires flying at 1000 feet; 4 Spitfires flying at 200 feet
    - The Sounds of War [disc 4 of 5], corwin_0356; Shellac disc
      Included on this disc are the sounds of: Anti-aircraft guns repelling attack by Messerschmidts on balloons at Dover
    - The Sounds of War [disc 5 of 5], corwin_0357; Shellac disc
      Included on this disc are the sounds of: Bombs falling; drone of plane; air raid siren - alert; all clear; naval anti-aircraft fire; diving plane
  - Alan Carmichael interviewing Norman Corwin, 09/23/1946; corwin_0097; Lacquer discs/acetates (Oversize 2)
    Interview by Alan Carmichael in Australia on Corwin's arrival in that country, September 23, 1946. The interview was broadcast the same evening over the network of the Australia Broadcasting Commission. On the sleeve's label is written: "Opening and closing announcement: not recorded". Also: "Predetermine start." Disc has two yellow lines.
  - Gambill, Norman / essay on Corwin, 11 Jun 1973; producer of Corwin Re-Recording Project at Syracuse University; "Early Radio Drama of Norman Corwin" plus photocopied research material (Box 29)
    Gift of Norman Gambill, 1973
  - Klein, Philip / term paper on Corwin (212), 1969; sent to Corwin by the author; includes letter from Klein (Box 29)
  - Lennart, Isobel / script, "Design for Sharing," read by Corwin, 1969 (Box 30)
  - Madsen, Roy / master's thesis on biographical movies (142 or 148), 1968; thesis on biographical movies; only those chapters dealing with the movie Lust for Life are included, along with two letters from Madsen (Box 30)
  - Malloy, Carolyne / master's thesis on Corwin's radio dramas (223), 1968 (Box 30)
  - McNett, Richard J. / term paper on Corwin (184), 1949; includes correspondence bewteen Corwin and the author (Box 30)
  - Munson, Ona / radio program, CBS Open House, Corwin as guest (93), 1944; script (Box 30)
  - O'Brien, Joel / radio program, The Corwin Cycle
    Broadcast over Station WNYC in New York City in the summer of 1942, these were originally produced the previous year on the CBS Series 26 BY CORWIN. Joel O'Brien directed. Corwin had no direct connection with the productions.
    - Three programs from the Corwin Cycle: Anne Rutledge, 1942; corwin_0266; Lacquer discs/acetates
      See also Productions by Corwin: Radio programs: Anne Rutledge.
    - Three programs from the Corwin Cycle: Appointment, 1942; corwin_0265; Lacquer discs/acetates (Oversize 7)
      See also Productions by Corwin: Radio programs: Appointment.
    - Three programs from the Corwin Cycle: Between Americans, 1942; corwin_0267; Lacquer discs/acetates
      See also Productions by Corwin: Radio programs: Between Americans.
    - Three programs from the Corwin Cycle: Daybreak, 1942; corwin_0271; Lacquer discs/acetates
      See also Productions by Corwin: Radio programs: Daybreak.
    - Three programs from the Corwin Cycle: Descent of the Gods, 1942; corwin_0268; Lacquer discs/acetates
      See also Productions by Corwin: Radio programs: Descent of the Gods.
    - Three programs from the Corwin Cycle: Fragment From a A Lost Cause, 1942; corwin_0264; Lacquer discs/acetates
      See also Productions by Corwin: Radio programs: Fragment from a Lost Cause.
    - Three programs from the Corwin Cycle: Good Heavens!, Sep 23, 1942; corwin_0263; Lacquer discs/acetates
      See also Productions by Corwin: Radio programs: Good Heavens!.
    - Three programs from the Corwin Cycle: Murder In Studio One, 1942; corwin_0269; Lacquer discs/acetates
      See also Productions by Corwin: Radio programs: Murder in Studio One and Productions by others: Weintraub, William Hobart.
    - Three programs from the Corwin Cycle: My Client Curley, 1942; corwin_0272; Lacquer discs/acetates (Oversize 8)
      See also Productions by Corwin: Radio programs: My Client Curley.
    - Three programs from the Corwin Cycle: Old Salt, 1942; corwin_0270; Lacquer discs/acetates (Oversize 7)
      See also Productions by Corwin: Radio programs: Old Salt.
    - Three programs from the Corwin Cycle: Radio Primer, Sep 23, 1942; corwin_0261; Lacquer discs/acetates
      See also Productions by Corwin: Radio programs: Radio Primer.
    - The Corwin Cycle: To Tim, at Twenty, May 27, 1942; corwin_0227; Lacquer discs/acetates (Oversize 6)
    - Three programs from the Corwin Cycle: Wolfeiana, Aug 18, 1942; corwin_0262; Lacquer discs/acetates
  - O'Neill, Eugene and Gassner, John / radio program, Author Meets Critic, discussing Corwin's Untitled
    Eugene O'Neill, Jr., John Gassner, John T. M. McCafferey, Norman Corwin discussing the book "UNTITLED" on the AUTHOR MEETS CRITIC program of May 1, 1947, on Radio Station WQXR in New York City. Gassner served as adversary, and O'Neill, Jr., defended the book. Only copy extant.
    - Author Meets Critic [disc 1 of 2], 05/01/1947; corwin_0224; Lacquer discs/acetates
    - Author Meets Critic [disc 2 of 2], 05/01/1947; corwin_0225; Lacquer discs/acetates
  - Rennie[?], Hedley / painting of Corwin (179), 1945; photocopy of oil portrait (Box 30)
  - Rewald, John / research paper, "Van Gogh in Paris" (46), 1955; research material compiled by John Rewald, possibly for use with Lust for Life (Box 30)
  - Earl Robinson Song for Corwin Series, corwin_0352; Lacquer discs/acetates
    In 1944, Earl Robinson, composer of "Lonesome Train" and "Ballad for Americans," recorded a son he wrote to "plug" Corwin's then forthcoming weekly radio series over CBS, entitled COLUMBIA PRESENTS CORWIN. (Corwin had earlier produced BALLAD FOR AMERICANS,and on the new series he produced and directed both THE LONESOME TRAIN and a one-act opera based on Carl Sandburg's THE PEOPLE, YES.)
  - [Ryan, Robert] SET YOUR CLOCK AT U-235, May 1960; corwin_0360; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 31)
    See also Radio programs: Set your clock at U-235 and Speeches: Set your clock at U-235.
    Tape of Robert Ryan reading SET YOUR CLOCK AT U-235, published as one of the plays in UNTITLED, page 509. Broadcast over Radio Station KPFK, Los Angeles. See also item #102 - printed text.
  - The Congo / The Plot to Overthrow Christmas / Mood Indigo, 11/22/1963; corwin_0374; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 31)
    Typed description accompanying item reads as follows: "Choric reading of excerpts from / THE PLOT TO OVERTHROW CHRISTMAS / by the San Diego State Verse Choir, under the direction of Prof. E. K. Povenmire. Performed at Pacific Beach Junior High School, Cal., on Nov. 22, 1966."
  - Schoenstein, Ralph / book, Time Lurches On, dedicated to Corwin (196), 1965 (Box 30)
  - Sherman, Richard / screenplay, "Message for Uncle Billy," connection to Corwin unknown (41), alternate title, "Escape from Andersonville"; rough first draft (Box 30)
  - Van Doren, Carl / foreword to special edition of Thirteen by Corwin, 1942; limited print edition, distributed by CBS; manuscript, galleys (Box 30)
  - Janet Waldo Reading Excerpts from Corwin Shows, corwin_0226; Lacquer discs/acetates
    Miss Waldo, who starred for many years in the radio serial CORLISS ARCHER, made her own selection of material from early Corwin broadcasts - SEEMS RADIO IS HERE TO STAY, GOOD HEAVENS, and PSALM FOR A DARK YEAR. She read these to organ accompaniment. Corwin did not direct; he knew nothing of the reading, and was presented the record some time later. The disc was distributed among material that was circulated by the Armed Forces Radio Service during the war. Mrs. Waldo was the wife of Robert E. Lee, co-author of INHERIT THE WIND, AUNTIE MAE, and other plays and musicals.
  - Weintraub, William Hobart / proposed radio program Studio One, to be produced by Corwin
    See also Productions by Corwin: Radio programs: Murder in Studio One and Productions by others: O'Brien, Joel.
    - Proposal package (30), circa 1944; includes blurbs about Corwin, summary of what the show would be about, etc. (Box 30)
    - Studio One, 04/24/1943; corwin_0288; Lacquer discs/acetates
      Promotional recording for Studio One, a projected series offered for commercial sponsorship by William Hobart Weintraub, ca. 1944-5. Joseph Julian, whom Corwin had cast as the American on AN AMERICAN IN ENGLAND in 1942, appears on this disc. Corwin's only contribution to this aural prospectus was the title. Though the series never became a reality, the title was used - with Corwin's permission - by his friend Fletcher Markle for a sustaining drama series over CBS, and later it was adopted by - and sponsored by - the Ford Motor Company. The title STUDIO ONE also moved intact over to television, where for some time it served as the name of one of the foremost dramatic programs.